you
Krishnamurti in dialogue with Dr. Alan
W. Anderson. J. Krishnamurti was born in
South India and educated in England. For
the past 40 years he has been speaking
in the United States, Europe, India,
Australia, and other parts of the world.
From the outset of his life's
work he repudiated all connections with
organized religions and ideologies and said
that his only concern was to set
men absolutely unconditionally free. He is
the author of many books, among them
The Awakening of Intelligence, The Urgency
of Change, Freedom from the Known, and
The Flight of the Eagle. This is
one of a series of dialogues between Krishnamurti
and Dr. Alan W. Anderson, who
is professor of religious studies at San
Diego State University where he teaches
Indian and Chinese scriptures and the
oracular tradition. Dr. Anderson, a
published poet, received his degree from
Columbia University and the Union
Theological Seminary. He has been honored
with a Distinguished Teaching Award
from the California State Universities.
Mr. Krishnamurti, last time we were
speaking you made the remark that fear
and pleasure are opposite sides of the
same coin and as I remember when we
concluded our last conversation we were
still talking about fear and I was
thinking perhaps we could move from
fear into the discussion of pleasure but
perhaps there's something more about fear that
we need still to look into to
explore.
Sir, I think for most of us
fear has created such misery
so many activities born of fear,
ideologies and gods that we never seem
to be free completely from
fear. That's what we were saying.
And so freedom from and freedom are two different things.
Aren't they? Freedom from fear and
the feeling of being completely free.
Would you say that the notion even
of freedom for is also a suggestion of
conflict? Yes, yes. Do go ahead. Yes.
Freedom for and freedom from has this
contradiction in itself and therefore
conflict and therefore a battle, a
violence, a struggle. When one understands that
rather deeply then one can see the
meaning of what it means to be free.
Not from or for but intrinsically, deeply by
itself. Probably it's a non-verbal,
non-ideational happening. I see. A feeling
that all the burden has fallen away
from you. Not that you are struggling to
throw them away. The burdens don't
exist. Conflicts don't exist. As we were
saying the other day, relationship then
is in total freedom. Your word intrinsic
interested me. Sometimes I think in
our tongue we will use the adverbial
preposition in. Would it be possible to
say freedom in or would you not even
want to have in? Not in, no. Far
in, from. They're all out. Yes, yes, go on.
Please do. So these two principles, pleasure and fear,
seems to be deeply rooted in us.
These two principles of pleasure and fear. I
don't think we can understand pleasure
without understanding fear. I see, I see.
You can't separate them really but
for investigating one has to separate them.
Yes. Were it not for fear do you
think we should ever have thought? We would
never have got the notion. I
understand, I understand. It's like punishment and
reward. Yes. If there was no punishment
at all then nobody would talk about
reward. Yes, I see. So, and when
we're talking about pleasure I think we ought
to be clear that we're not
condemning pleasure. We're not trying to become
puritanical or permissive. We're trying
to investigate or examine, explore the
whole structure and nature of pleasure as we
did fear. As we did fear. And to do
that properly and deeply the
attitude of condemnation or acceptance of
pleasure must be set aside. It seems
natural. Yes. I mean if I want to
investigate something I must be
free from my inclinations, prejudices. The
looking forward to is, I see, beginning
to emerge from what you're saying. Yes.
We say we look forward to pleasure. We
even ask a person, don't we, what is
your pleasure? Yes. We get nervous in
thinking that perhaps we won't meet it.
Now, I take it that what
you're saying suggests the anticipation of
gratification here. Would that be
right? Yes, that's right. Gratification,
satisfaction and sense of fulfilment. We'll
go into all that when we
talk about pleasure. But we must be clear
from the beginning, I think, that we are
not condemning it. The priests throughout
the world have condemned it. Yes. The
notion of freedom is associated with
many religious approaches to this. One is
free from desire. Yes. One has to bear
in mind that we are not justifying it or
sustaining it or condemning it but observing
it. Yes. To really go into the
question of pleasure, I think one
has to look into desire first.
The more commercial
and the usage of things, the more
desire grows. You can see
it, commercialism and consumption of
things. You can see it, commercialism
and consumerism, through propaganda, desire is
flame, you know, sustained, is pushed forward, is
– what is the word I'm looking for?
– is nourished, expanded, nurtured, inflamed
– that's the word – inflamed. Yes.
And you see this happening right through the
world now. In India, for example – not
that I know India much better than I do
America because I have not lived there very long,
I go there every year – this desire
and its instant fulfilment is beginning to take
place. Before, in the Brahmanical, orthodox sense,
there was a certain restraint, a certain
traditional discipline which says, don't be
concerned with the world and things, they
are not important. What is important is
the discovery of truth, Brahman, reality and so
on. But now all that is gone, now the
desire is being inflamed by more. Don't be satisfied
with two trousers but have a dozen
trousers. This feeling of excitement in possession is
stimulated through commercialism,
consumerism and propaganda.
A. There's a lot of terror, isn't
there, associated with commercialism, on the part
of those who are purveyors in this, because
the pleasure fades off and this requires a
stronger stimulus next time.
That's what the couturiers are doing. Every year
there is a new fashion, or every six
months or every month, I don't know what
it is. There is the stimulation of desire.
It is really quite frightening, in a
sense, how people are using or stimulating desire
to acquire money, possessions, the whole circle
of a life that is utterly sophisticated, a
life in which there is instant fulfilment of
one's desire, and the feeling if you don't
act there is frustration. So
all that is involved in it.
A. Would you say then that the approach to
this, on the part of what you have described,
is on the basis of frustration. Frustration
itself is regarded as the proper incentive.
And since frustration itself is a nullity, we
are trying to suggest that nullity is in
itself interested in being filled, whereas in
fact it couldn't be by its nature.
K. Right.
K. And I think children don't frustrate
them. Let them do what they like.
A. Yes. That reminds me of something years
ago in graduate school. I was brought up as
a child in England in a rather
strict way compared with the permissiveness of today.
And one of my graduate colleagues told me
that he had been brought up by his parents
in a totally permissive way. This was at Columbia
University. And he looked at me and he said,
I think you were better off because
at least you had some intelligible reference against
which to find out who you are, even if
what you found out wasn't right, there was something
Whereas I had to do it entirely on my
own and I still haven't done it. And he talked
about himself as being constantly in the world trying
to hide the fact that he was a nervous
wreck. We had a long conversation over dinner. Yes.
K. Sir, I think it is before we
enter into the complicated field of pleasure, we ought
to go into this question of desire.
A. Yes, yes, yes. I'd like to do that.
K. I mean, desire seems to be
a very active and demanding instinct, demanding activity
that's going on in us all
the time. So what is desire?
A. I wonder if I could ask you to
relate it to appetite as over against what one would
call hunger that is natural. Sometimes I've found
a confusion that seems to be a confusion
to me and that's why I'm asking you.
Someone will get the idea in class talking about
the question of appetite and desire that if
we look to nature, the lion desires to kill
the antelope to satisfy his appetite. Whereas it
has seemed to me the correct reply to that
is, no, that's not the case. The lion
wants to incorporate the antelope into his own
substance. He's not chasing his appetite.
K. I mean, I think they are
both related, appetite and desire. Appetite, physical appetite,
and there is psychological appetite, which
is much more complex, sexual appetite, and
the appetite, intellectual appetite, a sense of curiosity.
A. Even more furious.
K. More furious, that's right. So I
think both desire and appetite are stimulated by
commercialism, by consumerism, which is
the present civilization actively operating in
the world at the present time, both in
Russia, everywhere, this consumerism has to be fulfilled.
That's what...
A. Right. We talk about planned obsolescence.
K. Planned obsolescence, quite, quite.
A. You have that in mind, yes, I see.
K. So what is appetite and what is
desire? I have an appetite because I'm hungry. That's
a natural appetite. I see a car and I've read
a great deal about it and I like to possess
it, drive it, feel the power of it,
going fast, the excitement of all that. That's
another form of appetite.
A. Yes.
K. Appetite, intellectual appetite, of discussing
with a clever, intelligent, observing man
or woman, to discuss, to stimulate each other in discussion.
A. Yes.
K. And comparing each other's
knowledge, a kind of subtle fight.
A. Making points.
K. Points, that's right. And that is very stimulating.
A. Oh yes, yes it is.
And there is the appetite, sexual
appetite, the sexual appetite of constantly thinking
about it, chewing the cud, all
that, both psychological and physical appetites, normal,
abnormal, the feeling of fulfilment and frustration,
all that is involved in appetite. And I'm
not sure whether religions, organised religions
and beliefs, whether they would not stimulate
a peculiar appetite for rituals.
A. I have the notion they do. It
seems to me that despite pious protestations against
that, there is a theatrical display that occurs.
K. Oh, obviously. You go to a Catholic mass
and you see the beauty of it, the beauty of
colour, the beauty of the setting,
the whole structure, it's marvellously theatrical and
beautiful.
A. And for the moment it
appears that we have heaven on earth.
K. Yes, that's tremendously stimulating.
A. But then we have to go out again.
And it's all stimulated through tradition,
through usage of words, chants and certain
association of words, symbols, images, flowers,
incense, all that is very, very stimulating.
And if one is used to that, one misses it.
Oh, yes, yes. I was thinking as you
were saying about, at least to my ear, extraordinarily
beautiful a language of Sanskrit, and the
chanting of the Gita and the swaying back
and forth, and then one sits down to study
what the words say and one says to himself,
now look, what on earth is going on when
we're doing this as over against what the word itself
could disclose. But the seduction that
is available, of course it's self-seduction,
one can't blame the language for being beautiful.
K. No, it's self-diss...
A. It's a self-diss... yes. And all this
is encouraged. And the notion I take that you're
suggesting that we look at here is
that there's a tremendously invested interest in keeping
this up.
K. Of course.
A. Yes.
K. And commercial it is. And if it
is not sustained by the priest, the whole thing
would collapse. So is this a battle to
hold the human being in his appetites, which is
really very frightening when you look at
it. Frightening in the sense, rather disgusting
in one way, exploiting people, and
intrinsically destructive to the human mind.
A. Yes, yes. I've had this problem in teaching,
in my classes, in terms of my own discussion
Sometimes it has seemed that maybe the first stanza
of a poem that I will have known by
heart would be appropriate. And so I'll begin to
recite it. And when I get to the end of
it, the expectation has arisen, the ears
are there, the bodies are leaning forward, and
I have to stop, you see, and I have to
say, well now, you see, we can't go on because
you're not listening to what I'm saying,
you're listening to how it's being said. And
if I read it terribly, you would no more
listen to what it is, your disgust would dominate,
just as the pleasure is dominating now. And
students have got after me for not reciting
more poetry. You see, that you would be upset
with that is a perfect sign that you haven't
started to do your work in class yet.
And then we're up against the problem that they
think I'm being ascetical and denying the good.
K. Denying the good, yes. Good, quite, quite.
A. That's part of what you...
K. Yes, of course.
A. Good, good. I'm glad
you cleared that for me. Yes.
K. And there is this desire, appetite, we know
more or less, we have a little bit gone
into it. What is desire? Because I see something,
immediately I must have it. A gown, a coat,
a tie, the feeling of possession, the urge
to acquire, the urge to experience, the urge
to offer an act that will give
me tremendous satisfaction. The satisfaction might be the
acquisition, acquiring a tie or a coat or
sleeping with a woman or having a quarry.
Now, behind that isn't there, sir, this desire?
I might desire a house and another might
desire a car, another might desire
to have intellectual knowledge, another might desire
a god or enlightenment. They are all the same.
The objects vary, but the desire is the same.
One I call the noble, the other I
call the ignoble, worldly, stupid. But the desire
is the desire behind it. So what is desire?
How does it come about that this very strong
desire is born, is cultured? You follow? What
is desire? How does it take place in each
one of us?
A. If I have understood you, you have
made a distinction between on the one hand appetite
associated with natural hunger, that sort of
desire, and now we are talking about desire
which sometimes gets the name artificial. I
don't know whether you would want to call
it that, but sometimes...
Desire. I might desire, but
the objects vary, sir, don't they?
Yes, the objects vary.
Objects of desire vary according to each
individual, each tendency and idiosyncrasy or conditioning
and so on. Desire for that and that and that.
But I want to find out what is desire? How
does it come about? I
think it is fairly clear that.
You see, sir...
A. Do you mean a sense of absence?
K. No, no. I am asking
what is desire? How does it come?
A. One would have to ask himself.
K. Yes, I am asking you how does it come
about that there is this strong desire for or against
desire itself. I think it is clear.
Perception, visual perception, then there is sensation,
then there is contact, and desire comes out
of it. That is the process, isn't it?
A. Oh yes, yes. I am quite clear now
what you are saying. I have been listening very hard.
K. Perceptions, contact, sensation, desire.
A. And then if the desire is frustrated, anger.
K. All the rest of it follows. So,
desire. So the religious people, monks, throughout the world
said, be without desire, control desire, suppress desire,
or if you cannot, transfer it to something
that is worthwhile, God, or enlightenment,
or truth, or this or that.
A. But then that is just
another form of desire, not to desire.
K. Not to desire, of course.
A. So we never get out of that.
K. But you see, they say control.
A. Yes. Power is brought into play now.
K. Control, desire. Because you need energy to serve God.
And if you are caught in desire,
you are caught in a tribulation, in trouble,
which will dissipate your energy, therefore
hold it, control it, suppress it.
You have seen this, sir. I
have seen it so often in Rome.
The priests are walking along with the Bible.
And they don't look at anything else, they
keep on reading it, because they are attracted.
It doesn't matter if it's a woman or a
nice house, or a nice cloth, or so on.
So keep looking at it. Never
expose yourself to tribulation, to temptation.
So hold it, because you
need your energy to serve God.
A. So desire comes about
through visual perception, contact, sensation, desire.
That's the process of it.
And then there's the whole backlog of memory
of that in the past to reinforce it.
I was taken with what you just said.
Here's this book that's already outside me.
It's really no more than what they
put on horses when they're on a race.
K. Blinkers. The Bible becomes a blinker.
A. The blinking Bible. Yes, I follow that.
But the thing that caught me
was never quietly looking at it.
K. That's it, sir. A. The desire itself. Yes.
I walked once behind a group of monks
in India, and they were very serious monks.
The elderly monk with his disciples around him, they
were walking up a hill, and I followed them.
They never once looked at the
beauty of the sky, the blue,
the extraordinary blue of the sky in the mountains,
and the blue light of grass and
the trees and the birds and the water.
Never once looked around.
They were concerned, and they had bent their head down,
and they were repeating something, which
I happen to know in Sanskrit,
and going along, totally unaware of nature,
totally unaware of the passers-by,
because their whole life has
been spent in controlling desire
and concentrating on what they
thought was the way to reality.
So desire there acted as a repressive, limiting process.
A. Of course.
K. Because they were frightened. If
I look, there might be a woman.
I might be tempted.
Cut it.
So, we see what desire is,
and we see what appetite is.
They are similar.
A. Yes. Would you say appetite
was a specific focus of desire?
K. Yes, put it that way.
Yes. But they both go together.
A. Oh, yes.
K. They are two different words for the same thing.
Now, a problem arises.
Need there be a control of desire at all?
You follow, sir?
A. Yes, I am asking myself, because in our conversations
I have learned that every time you ask a question,
if I take that question and construe
it in terms of a syllogistical relation
to things that have been stated as premises before,
I am certainly not going to come to the answer
that is not the right answer,
is over against the wrong answer.
I am not going to come
to the one answer that is needful.
So every time you have asked me this morning,
I have asked myself inside. Yes, please go ahead.
The discipline is a form
of suppression and control of desire.
Religious, sectarian, non-sectarian,
it is all based on that – control.
Control your appetite, control your desires,
control your thought,
and this control gradually squeezes
out the flow of free energy.
I don't know if I can...
A. Oh, yes, yes, yes.
And yet, amazingly, the Upanishads in particular
have been interpreted in terms
of tapas as encouraging this control.
K. I know, I know.
In India it is something fantastic.
The monks who have come to
see me, they are called sannyasis,
they have come to see me, they are incredible.
If I can tell you, a monk
who came to see me some years ago,
quite a young man,
he left his house and home at
the age of 15 to find God,
and he had renounced everything, put on the robe,
and as he began to
grow older, at 18, 19, 20,
his sexual appetite was something burning.
He explained to me how it became intense,
he had taken a vow of
celibacy, as sannyasis do, monks do.
And he said, day after day,
in my dreams, in my walk,
in my going to house, begging,
this thing was becoming so like a fire.
Do you know what he did to control it?
A. No, no. What did he
do? K. He had it operated.
A. Oh, for heaven's sake. Is that a fact?
K. That...
K. Sir, no, his urge for
God was so... you follow, sirs?
A. Yes.
K. The idea, the idea, not the reality.
A. Not the reality, no.
K. Sir, he came to see me.
He had heard several talks which had given that place.
He came to see me in tears.
He said, now what have I done? You follow, sir?
A. Oh, I'm sure. Yes.
K. What have I done to myself?
I cannot repair it.
I cannot grow a new organ.
It's finished.
And we... Oh, he was insane.
That's the extreme.
But all control is in that direction.
I don't know if I'm...
A. Yes, this is terribly dramatic.
The one who is sometimes called
the first Christian theologian, Origen,
castrated himself out of, as I understand it,
a misunderstanding of the words of Jesus.
If your hand offends you, cut it off.
Authority to me is criminal in these directions.
It doesn't matter who says it.
A. And like the monk that you just described,
Origen came later to repent of this
in terms of seeing that it
has nothing to do with anything.
It's just a terrible thing.
Was this monk, if I may ask,
also saying to you in his tears that
he was absolutely no better off
in any way, shape or form?
K. No, on the contrary.
He said, I've committed a sin.
I've committed an evil act.
A. Yes, yes, of course.
K. He realised what he had done.
That through that way... nothing.
A. Nothing.
I've met so many, not such extreme forms
of control and denial, but others,
they have tortured themselves for an idea.
You follow, sir? For a symbol, for a concept.
And I've sat with them, discussed with them,
and they begin to see
what they have done to themselves.
I met a man who
was high up in a bureaucracy,
and one morning he woke up and he said,
I'm passing judgement in court over others, punishment.
And I seem to say to them, I know truth.
You don't, you're punished.
So one morning he woke up
and he said, this is all wrong.
I must find out what truth is.
So he resigned, left, and went away for 25 years.
To find out what truth is.
Sir, these people are dreadfully serious, you understand?
They're not like cheap repeaters of some mantra
and such rubbish.
So somebody brought him to the talks I was giving,
and he came to see me the next day.
He said, you're perfectly right.
I have been meditating on truth for 25 years,
and it has been self-hypnosis, as you pointed out.
I have been caught in
my own verbal, intellectual formula, structure,
and I haven't been able to get out of it.
You understand, sir?
A.S. – 25 years.
That's a very moving story.
K. – And to admit that
it is wrong needs courage, needs perception.
A.S. – Exactly.
Now, courage, perception.
So, now that's singing all this, sir.
The permissiveness on one side,
the reaction to Victorian way of life,
the reaction to the world
with all its absurdities and trivialities and banalities,
all that absurdity,
and the reaction to that is to renounce that,
to say, but I won't touch it.
But desire is burning all the same.
All the glands are working.
You can't cut away your glands.
So therefore they said, control.
Therefore they said, don't be attracted to a woman.
Don't look at the sky,
because the sky is so marvellously beautiful,
and beauty then may become the beauty of a woman,
the beauty of a house,
the beauty of a chair
in which you can sit comfortably.
So don't look, control it.
You follow, sir?
The permissiveness, the reaction to restrained control,
the pursuit of an idea as God,
and for that control, desire.
And I met a man again.
He left his house at the age of 20.
He is really quite extraordinary chap he was.
He was 75 when he came to see me.
He had left home at the age of 20,
renounced everything and all that,
and went from teacher to teacher to teacher.
He went to – I won't mention names,
because that wouldn't be right –
and he came to me, talked to me.
He said, I went to all these people asking
if they could help me to find God.
I have spent from the age
of 20 till I am 75,
wandering all over India.
I have been a very serious man,
and not one of them has told me the truth.
I have been to the most
famous, to the most socially active,
the people who talk endlessly about God.
After all these years,
I return to my house and find nothing.
And you come along – he said to me –
you come along, you never talk about God.
You never talk about the path to God.
You talk about perception,
the seeing what is and going beyond it.
The beyond is the real, not the what is.
Now show me.
You understand?
You understand? He was 75.
A. Yes, 55 years on the road.
K. They don't do that in Europe, on the road.
He was literally on the road.
A. Yes, I am sure he was,
because you said he was in India.
K. Begging from village to village to village.
A. Yes.
K. When he told me I
was in so much mood, tears almost,
to spend a whole lifetime,
as they do in the business world,
50 years to go day after day to the office
and die at the end of it.
It is the same thing.
The feeling of desire, money, money, money, money,
more things, things, things,
and the other, none of that,
but another substitute for that.
A. Yes, just another form.
K. So, looking at all this, sir,
I know it is dreadful what
human beings have done to themselves
and to others.
Seeing all that,
one inevitably asks the question,
how to live with desire.
You can't help it, desire is there.
The moment I see something, a beautiful flower,
the admiration, the love of it, the smell of it,
the beauty of the petal,
the quality of the flower and so on,
the enjoyment,
one asks, is it possible to live
without any control whatsoever?
A. The very question is terrifying
in the context of these disorders
that you are speaking about.
I am taking the part now of
the perspective that one is in
when out of frustration he
comes to you, let us say,
like the man did after 55 years on the road,
the minute he walks in the door,
he has come to get something he doesn't already have.
And as soon as you make that statement,
if the answer that is coming up,
there is already where it starts if-ing right now,
if the answer is going to be something that
completely negates this whole investment
of 55 years on the road,
it seems that most persons
are going to freeze right there.
K. And it is a cruel thing too, sir.
He has spent 55 years at it
and suddenly realised what he has done,
the cruelty of deception, you follow?
Self-deception, deception of tradition,
you follow, of all the teachers
who have said control, control, control.
And he comes and says, and you say to him,
what place has control?
A. I think I am beginning
to get a very keen sense
of why you say, go into it,
because there is a place there like dropping a stitch,
we might say.
If he doesn't get past that initial shock,
then he is not going to go into it.
K. No.
A. Yes, yes, yes.
K. So we talk, I spent hours, we discussed,
we went into it, gradually he saw.
He said, quite right.
So, sir, unless we understand
the nature and the structure of appetite and desire,
which is more or less the same,
we cannot understand very deeply pleasure.
A. Yes, yes, yes.
I see why you have been
good enough to lay this foundation
before we get to the opposite side of the coin.
Because pleasure and fear are the two principles
that are active in most
human beings, in all human beings.
And that is reward and punishment.
Don't bring up a child through punishment, but reward him.
You know, the psychologists are advocating some of this.
A. Oh, yes, yes.
They are encouraged by the experiments on Pavlov's dogs.
K. Dogs or pigeons or ducks.
A. Right.
K. Do this and don't do that.
So, unless we understand fear,
understand in the sense, investigate,
see the truth of it, and go,
if the mind is capable of going beyond it,
to be totally free of fear,
as we discussed the other day,
and also to understand the nature of pleasure.
Because pleasure is an extraordinary thing.
To see a beautiful thing and
enjoy it, what is wrong with it?
Nothing. Nothing. Nothing.
But see what is involved in it.
A. Right. The mind plays a trick there.
I say to myself, I
can't find anything wrong with it,
therefore nothing is wrong with it.
But I don't really believe that necessarily.
And I was thinking a little while ago,
when you were speaking about the attempts through power
to negate desire through power.
K. Because search for power.
Negating desire is search for power.
A. Would you be saying that one searches for power
in order to secure a pleasure
that has not yet been realised?
K. Yes.
A. I understood you well. K. Yes.
A. I see. Oh, it's a terrible thing.
K. But it is a reality.
A. Oh, it's going on. K. It's going on.
A. Oh, yes. But we are taught that from children.
K. That's just it, sir.
So, pick up any magazine, the advertisements,
the half-naked ladies, women, and so on, so on.
So, pleasure is a very
active principle in man, as fear.
A. Oh, yes.
K. And again, society, which is immoral, has said, control.
One side, the religious side, is control,
and commercialism says, don't control, enjoy, buy, sell.
You follow?
And the human mind goes, it's all right.
My own instinct is to
have pleasure, I'll go after it,
but Saturday and Sunday or Monday
or whatever the day it is,
I'll give it to God.
You follow, sir? A. Yes.
K. And this game goes on.
Forever it has been going on.
So, what is pleasure?
You follow, sir?
Why should pleasure be controlled?
I'm not saying it's right or wrong.
Please, let's be very clear from the beginning
that we are not condemning pleasure.
We are not saying you must
give reins to it, let it run,
or that it must be suppressed or justified.
We are trying to understand why pleasure has become
such extraordinary importance in life.
Pleasure of enlightenment, you follow, sir?
Pleasure of sex, pleasure of possession,
pleasure of knowledge, pleasure of power.
A. Heaven, which is regarded as the ultimate pleasure.
K. Of course.
A. Is usually spoken of, theologically, as the future state.
K. Yes.
A. This is, to me, very interesting
in terms of what you've been saying.
And even at the level of gospel songs
we hear when the road is called up yonder,
I'll be there when it's called up yonder.
K. Yes, quite, quite, quite.
A. Which means at the end of the line.
And then there's the terror
that I won't be good enough.
K. When that.
A. Yes. So I'm tightening up my belt
to pay my heavily insured policy on Saturday and Sunday,
the two days of the weekend that you mentioned.
What if you got caught from Monday through Friday?
Yes.
So, pleasure, enjoyment, and joy.
You follow, sir?
There are three things in one.
A. Three things.
K. Pleasure, enjoyment, and joy.
Happiness, that is, joy is happiness.
Ecstasy, the delight,
the sense of tremendous enjoyment.
And what is the relationship of pleasure
to enjoyment and to joy and happiness?
You follow?
A. Yes, we've been moving a long way from fear.
K. Fear, that's right.
A. But I don't mean moving away
by turning our back on it.
K. No, no, we have gone into it.
This is the movement from that to this.
It's not away from.
A. No.
K. Pleasure.
There is a delight in seeing something very beautiful.
Delight, if you are at all sensitive,
if you are all observant,
if there is a feeling of relationship to nature,
which very few people unfortunately have,
they stimulate it,
but the actual relationship to nature,
that is, when you see something
really marvellously beautiful,
like a mountain with shadows, valleys,
and the line,
you know, it's something, a tremendous delight.
Now see what happens.
At that moment there is nothing but that.
That is, beauty of the mountain, lake,
or a single tree on a hill,
that beauty has knocked everything out of me.
A. Oh, yes.
K. And at that moment
there is no division between me and that.
There is a sense of great purity and enjoyment.
A. Exactly. Exactly.
K. Now then, see what takes place.
A. I see we have reached a point
where we are going to take a new step.
I feel it coming on.
It's amazing how this thing has moved so inevitably,
but not unjoyfully.
Not unjoyfully.
In our next conversation I would just love to...
K. We are going on. Is it time?